Hello guys, so thank you for considering this amazing course, which is a complete comprehensive MLOps
course with end to end data science project.
In this video, I will be talking about the life cycle of a data science project.
What does a big data engineer specifically do?
What does a data scientist actually do?
You know?
And in this entire course, what all MLOps tools we are going to specifically cover and how it is basically
going to use in which module it is basically going to use.
We'll talk about them.
Right.
So if you probably see this, I've created so many diagrams and here I have, I have just put up the
logo of every MLOps tools that we are covering in this course.
Okay.
So we have DVC, we have MLflow, we have Apache Airflow, we have astronomer, we have git, we have
GitHub, we have AWS, we have Docker, we have GitHub action.
We have Amazon SageMaker.
We have Grafana.
We have MongoDB.
We have Postgres Grace.
And we have Python.
Um, along with this, you know, one more cloud that I've actually used in one of the project is about
Azure.
Okay.
So Azure is also covered over here.
Uh, I've shown the deployment how you can probably convert that into a Docker container and probably
deploy in Azure Web container itself.
Right.
Web app itself.
So everything will be discussing in this specific course.
But before going ahead.
Right.
You really need to understand what is an MLOps engineer specifically do in an end to end data science
project.
So first I will talk about the life cycle of a data science project.
So if you probably see this two diagrams, this one diagram and the other diagram over here, this is
more about the life cycle of a data science project.
And then what we'll do is that while we are discussing this life cycle, where all which all MLOps tools
will be using, where, you know, because in our end to end data science project that we have discussed
in this particular course, we will also be including this entire MLOps tool.
Okay.
So here, um, see, understand in order to understand the life cycle of a data science project.
So first of all, let's say that there is a data science project or a big data engineering project,
right?
So first of all, the first task, the first step is basically with the requirement that gatherings,
you know, now in the requirement gathering, we have uh, domain experts or product owner along with
business analyst.
So if you are probably seeing in a data science team, uh, they will only not be data scientist or
data analyst.
They will be a lot of different roles and responsibilities like domain expert or product owner.
You'll also be having business analyst.
And all right.
So let's say that these two group of people are like these two people.
Right.
And when I say domain expert or product owner, this person will be having an extreme good amount of
domain knowledge with respect to this particular data science project.
Let's say this particular project is coming from a product based company.
Right.
So the data science project may be coming from a retail department.
It may be coming from the e-commerce department.
It may be coming from different different departments.
Right.
And here with respect to this particular use case, we are going to solve this data science project.
So obviously the person who is experienced in this domain will be the product owner.
Right.
So this person will know that what is that data science project that they really want to implement?
Okay.
Now this person along with the business analyst.
So here business analyst are the most luckiest people.
What I feel because if your if your uh uh if your specifically like if your client is in some different
foreign countries and also you really get a good amount of chance to interact with them travel, travel
the whole world itself.
Right.
So this business analyst, along with the domain expert or product owner, they will have a lot of discussion
and they will jot down all the requirements.
Right.
So uh, they will write down all the requirements.
So here the entire requirements will be prepared.
And they will write down all the requirements like uh, what all stories needs to be completed and they
will try to divide this entire story in the form of sprints.
Okay, so here in a data science project, also we are in most of the companies.
They follow an agile process.
Now agile process basically means like they are different different process of development.
You know we specifically use agile process.
There is like waterfall model and all.
So in most of the data science project, what I have seen in my experience, they usually follow an
agile process where they create sprints like there will be sprint one, there will be sprint two, and
each and every sprint they will try to divide this requirements like which all modules needs to be developed
in sprint one, which all module needs to be developed in sprint two.
So once that requirements is basically written down okay, then all these requirements are sent to the
data analyst or data scientist team specifically in a data science project.
Now again, this data analyst and data science team will have a discussion with the domain expertise
or product owner and they will try to find out like what all data, what all data will be required in
order to solve this particular project.
Okay.
Solve this particular problem.
So they will be identifying the data right.
They will be specifically identifying the data.
Now when I say identifying the data that basically means, uh, you know, they'll try to identify the
source of the data okay.
Now data may be present in the internal database.
It may be present in a third party or cloud API.
It may also be an API data.
It may be an IoT data also.
Right.
Uh, in in my previous companies where I was working with electronics goods, you know, there we had
lot of IoT devices and we used to capture those specific data.
So we need to identify the data and to identify the data.
Again, we will be requiring the help of a product owner or domain expertise because they may also be
having the data within the company.
They may be dependent on some third parties and all.
So those kind of data, they will first of all identify.
Once they identify the data source then here my big data engineering team will come into picture now,
because this big data engineering team will now create a data pipeline.
Data pipeline.
Now, this data pipeline is created in such a way that, first of all, whichever source we are identifying,
right, we will capture all this particular source, and then we will combine all those data in the
form of data pipeline.
Right.
Now, one of the most common data pipeline that you will be seeing in the industries that will be done
by the big data engineering team, it is nothing but the ETL pipeline.
Okay, ETL pipeline.
Now this ETL pipeline is nothing but extract, transform and load okay.
We basically extract from multiple data sources.
We do some kind of transformation, and then we finally load that entire combined data into some data
source like MongoDB.
It can be PostgreSQL and all.
So here we will be covering this entire ETL pipeline.
Also I have taken a couple of projects and I will show you how an ETL pipeline will be used.
And we will specifically use Apache Airflow over here.
And this is one of the amazing MLOps tool, uh, which is basically used to create this ETL pipeline,
because this actually helps you to schedule the right schedule.
Because if let's say that my data is basically coming from third party API every day, I need to probably
get that particular data so I can actually schedule this with the help of Apache Airflow.
Okay.
And we will be creating this ETL pipeline.
So here in this MLOps project, you know, my main aim was to give you the, uh, the crux of each and
everything.
Like how does a big data engineering team work?
Because here we'll focus on deployment also how to deploy this entire ETL pipeline.
So I will be focusing on that right.
So in this particular uh like in one of the modules right.
We will be discussing about data pipeline.
We will be discussing about ETL pipeline.
We'll also be doing the deployment.
And for this we'll be using AWS cloud and all.
Okay.
So uh that is what a big data engineer team does.
They actually create amazing data pipelines wherein they integrate with multiple data sources and then
try to combine the data and they load it into a specific data source.
Once that data source is, let's say the data source over here is used as MongoDB, right?
So once this entire data is basically loaded in the MongoDB, this will keep on getting updated in a
daily basis or in a weekly basis.
That depends on the data.
That is probably coming from the third party APIs or any other data source.
Okay.
Now once this is done, then our life cycle of a data science project comes.
Now, just by understanding this, you are able to understand that how many different roles and responsibilities
are there, right?
One of the roles and responsibilities over here are like product owner.
Then you have business analyst, then you have data scientist, then data analyst, then you have big
data engineering team, right.
And this entire MLOps course I will cover each and every thing with respect to this, right.
Obviously, I will not be covering product owner or business analyst because that is more of a documentation
kind of things.
They use tools like JIRA confluence to write down all the requirements.
But here from this, identifying the data source and all, we will try to go ahead and implement it.
Now, once we go to the life cycle of a data science project.
Now the next thing will be that whatever data has been collected in the data source, right?
So let's say over here I will just try to connect this okay.
I will just try to go ahead and connect this.
Let's say this is my data source.
Uh, one of the data source that I have also used is like something called as PostgreSQL.
Okay.
It can be Postgres, it can be MongoDB.
In one of the example I have used MongoDB.
Okay.
So let's consider MongoDB MongoDB and this MongoDB will also be hosted in the cloud okay.
Now from this particular uh pipeline we are storing it in the MongoDB.
Now from the MongoDB, our life cycle of a data science project starts okay.
Now again, here we are.
Whenever we talk about life cycle or data science project, the first step, which I probably missed
over here, to write it down, it is nothing but data ingestion.
So here it is nothing but data Ingestion.
So this is the step before feature engineering.
So I would like to consider as this as my first step okay.
Then I go to this my next step.
Or let me do one thing.
Let me just draw it on the top so that it will be easy for you to understand.
Okay, so here my first step is nothing but data ingestion.
Data ingestion okay.
So here is my first step.
Then we go to feature engineering feature selection and all.
Now what is the work in data ingestion here.
Uh our main aim is to read the data from data source okay.
So whenever I talk about data ingestion I will be showing you how to read the data from cloud.
Let's say how to read the data from S3 bucket or AWS S3 bucket.
How to read the data from MongoDB It can also be how to read data from Postgres.
Right.
So all these kind of examples, we will try to cover it up.
Okay.
In the data ingestion.
Right.
And uh while we are probably, uh reading it, there will be separate MLOps tools that will be required.
One of the important MLOps tools that will be used over here is something called as DVC, DVC.
DVC basically means data versioning control.
Okay.
So here you will be able to see that I have used DVC.
So we'll be talking about like why DVC will be important over here.
Because data versioning is also important because with respect to every training that we do for our
model, right, it is important that we have a proper versioning of the data because tomorrow the data
may change.
It may also add some more features inside it.
It may change the entire data format itself which is coming from the data source.
Okay.
So here, uh, if I talk about DVC, DVC is one MLOps tools, which I'm actually going to use over here
in big data engineering team.
While we are creating the data pipeline, we will be specifically using airflow, you know, to probably
create the entire ETL pipeline.
Then after this, we go to the feature engineering.
Again, in this course we have not focused more on feature engineering or different types of feature
engineering.
Otherwise this course will go on very long.
But some basic feature engineering so that I show you in a specific end to end project complete end
to end project.
But, uh, if you probably see some other courses of mine like machine learning and all that, I have
focused more on feature engineering and feature selection.
Okay.
So this is one of the module like feature transformation where we specifically do EDA handling missing
values, handling outliers and all.
Then we have feature selection where we probably select the best features that is required for the model.
Now this is the most important step.
That is model creation and hyperparameter tuning.
Now for model creation hyperparameter tuning I will be using multiple models.
We will try to perform different different hyperparameter tuning will try to select the different parameters.
One example I've shown with the help of Hyperopt.
One example I've shown with Gridsearchcv.
CV.
And then you can also go ahead and try out.
I've also used Randomizedsearchcv in one example.
Okay.
So you will be able to see all this kind of hyperparameter tuning when I am doing it.
And the reason why I'm doing this, because after I perform the hyperparameter tuning, I have to log
each and every metrics.
And here I will be using something called as MLflow, because here we are going to probably track experiments.
So experiment tracking will happen over here.
Experiment tracking will happen over here.
Now this experiment tracking how it is basically happening.
And here we are specifically going to use MLflow.
Not only that will deploy this MLflow in remote repository or in AWS.
We are going to use a remote repository called a DAGs hub.
Right.
So if I talk about DAGs hub this is another remote repository.
We will be using that also.
Right.
So here specifically we will be using MLflow for experiment tracking.
And here you can see that MLflow is also one of the MLOps tools that we will be using over here.
my complete experiment tracking where we will be logging metrics, where we'll be logging each and every
parameter.
Okay.
Then, uh, we will be understanding about dockers, how to dockerize your container and all.
So here, uh, there is a detailed module about understanding about Dockers, how you can work with
Dockers and all.
Uh, everything like Docker compose, everything is basically explained in that particular module.
Then we have this model deployment next stage.
Uh, when I talk about model deployment, um, I'll be using clouds like AWS and Azure.
Okay.
So two clouds will be more than sufficient in this particular course.
In one of the course, I have, uh, in one of the module I have implemented both with AWS Azure.
In other I have specifically gone with AWS.
You know, um, I have also used, uh, AWS SageMaker.
So AWS SageMaker actually helps you to create the entire entire end to end, uh, you'll be able to
build, deploy, create endpoints directly inside your AWS infrastructure itself.
So that project is also probably taken over here.
Okay.
Then coming to the last stage, which is nothing but model monitoring.
Now model monitoring.
Uh, over here will we will try to visualize the, uh, model outputs or we'll try to write some rules
based on that.
We'll probably visualize things.
And for this also we are going to use an MLOps tool which is called as Grafana.
Okay.
So I will be using something called as Grafana.
And if I just show you the logo over here.
So Grafana is basically used.
Okay.
Uh, so this is the overall thing because based on this particular visualization that we are created
in the Grafana.
And I'll try to show you through the basic example like how a rules is basically set in the Grafana,
how the visualization is basically created, how each and every graph is created, and all that we'll
be discussing over here.
Okay.
So overall, uh, in this entire, uh, entire lifecycle of a data science project, creating life cycle
or creating a data science project will be very easy.
Uh, like you can also use a Jupyter notebook and probably create each and every thing.
But my main aim is to bring modularity.
Modularity in the.
We will try to write a modular code how an end to end project is basically created completely modular
how industries in industry.
We specifically create we will be using YAML, YAML files.
Right?
How to read a YAML file like params, YAML schema, YAML files.
Along with this are how how a complete pipeline is basically created.
We will be discussing about that and whenever we do the deployment right we do the deployment.
Over here we will be using something called as GitHub action.
Okay.
Now this GitHub action will actually help us to do the automated deployment okay.
Automated deployment.
So here we will be also showing you that how the GitHub actions can be created.
You know what are workflows.
How do you probably go ahead and create different different environments like you at or this that you
know it is up to you, right.
So that is what my main aim is to make it completely industry standard.
And the best thing about this course is that everything over here, all the tools are open source,
all the tools are open source.
Okay.
Now many people will be asking, now let me just go through the list of all the MLOps tools we are using.
So DVC.
I've already told you, I'll make you understand that in the data ingestion, we'll be using MLflow
specifically in the experiment tracking airflow in the creation of the ETL pipeline.
Then now there is something called as astronomer.
So astronomer actually provides a framework to manage the airflow okay.
So this specifically manages the airflow.
And along with this it provides a cloud platform to properly deploy the airflow.
So we'll be talking about astronomer then for my code tracking I will be using git right.
For the code tracking code commit I will be using git.
GitHub will be my repository because it is completely available for free Then AWS is the cloud platform
we'll be using.
We'll also be using AWS SageMaker.
As I said, to define workflows and all, we will be creating GitHub actions to Dockerize.
Our entire application will be using Docker's right.
Then you have Grafana.
This is specifically for visualization so that we'll be able to check the performance of our model.
Databases we will be specifically using MongoDB.
So again understand that I'm not going to teach completely from basics.
Uh, I'm considering this that, you know, at least one NoSQL or one SQL database.
Right.
Because I'll directly be writing the query and all.
And finally, the Python programming language, uh, is the programming language that we are going to
use.
Okay.
Now, as a prerequisite, you need to understand that at least you should know Python programming language.
You should know databases like MongoDB or PostgreSQL, at least how to write some kind of queries.
Okay, that will be more than sufficient.
Along with this, uh, some some some important, some some some basic understanding about git.
Okay.
But anyhow, what I have done is that I've given recordings of the entire Python.
I've given the recordings of entire git, and then step by step we will follow each and every like how
I've actually covered each and every modules over here.
Similarly, we will go ahead and cover over there.
One more I forgot to add as a logo that is nothing but DAGs hub.
So it is a remote repository.
And uh, we will also show you like if you are working in a collaborative environment, uh, how DAGs
will be useful.
So I hope you got an idea about the different, different things that we are going to cover in this
course.
Um, thank you for considering the course.
I hope you enjoy this particular course.
You learn a lot of things.
Everything will be practical oriented, and we'll try to develop all our projects like this end to end.
So yes, this was it from my side.
I'll see you in the next video.
So let's start the next module.
That is with respect to Python.
But before that we will go ahead and the installation of, you know, uh, the VSCode Anaconda and many
more things.
So yes, this was it from my side.
I'll see you all in the next video.